{"tossups": [{"question": "This city changed hands after the battle of Desio, but the winning family died out after Filippo Maria Visconti bore no heirs, leading to the creation of this city\u2019s Golden Ambrosian Republic. The Peace of Lodi ended this city\u2019s wars with Venice and established the Sforza family as the rightful rulers of this city. For the point, name this city in Northern Italy, the capital of Lombardy.", "answer": "<b> Milan</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s 1975 Family Protection Law expanded access to divorce to women, who had earned the right to vote in the 1963 White Revolution. Those reforms were instituted by Reza Pahlavi, but this country rolled back those reforms after a 1979 revolution brought Ayatollah Khomeini [ko-MEH-nee] to power. For the point, name this Middle Eastern country in which, in a 1998 show of progress, two women were allowed to watch a men\u2019s World Cup qualifying match in Tehran.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of<b> Iran</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Battle of Magnesia followed one battle fought at the same site as this battle. 700 Thessalians were slaughtered and a force of Phocians were bypassed during this battle, where one leader replied \u201ccome and take them\u201d when asked prior to this battle to lay down his arms. Ephialtes [eff-EE-all-TEES] led the Immortals through a mountain pass to outflank the losers of this battle, which was fought at the same time as the Battle of Artemesium. For the point, name this battle, where Xerxes II forced a last stand by Leonidas and 300 Spartans.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Thermopylae</b> [therm-AH-puh-lee]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The \u201cSmoking Him Out\u201d cartoon depicted Democratic supporters of this party setting a barn on fire while proclaiming \u201cLong life to Davy Wilmot.\u201d It nominated Martin van Buren for the 1848 presidential election in its founding year, but the Compromise of 1850 led most of its moderate members to leave the party. For the point, name this 19th century American single-issue political party named for its opposition to slavery?", "answer": "<b> Free Soil</b> Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This company\u2019s CEO, Kazuo Hirai, pressured Amy Pascal to edit one of this company\u2019s films so that Kim Jong-Un\u2019s head would not explode. The \u201cGuardians of Peace\u201d demanded that this company cancel that Seth Rogen film,<em> The Interview</em>, and released a series of hacked internal e-mails from this company. For the point, name this Japanese company, whose other entertainment products include the Playstation.", "answer": "<b> Sony</b> (accept<b> Sony</b> Pictures Entertainment Inc.; accept<b> Sony</b> Computer Entertainment Company Inc.)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Seven months after attending a meeting in Paris to accept this program, Czech Foreign Minister Jan Mazaryk was thrown out of his bathroom window. Vyacheslav [vich-ih-SLAV] Molotov rejected this program for the entire Eastern Bloc, and its first action supplemented the Truman Doctrine by funding Greece and Turkey. The U.K. and France received the most aid from, for the point, what program in which the United States provided $13 billion to rebuild Europe following World War 2?", "answer": "<b> Marshall</b> Plan (or<b> European Recovery Program</b> or<b> ERP</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Missouri governor Lilburn Boggs attempted to reduce this man\u2019s power by issuing the Extermination Order. His failed joint stock company, Kirtland Safety Society, led him to relocate in an area he called\u201cZion\u201d. This man\u2019s order to destroy the facilities of the newspaper<em> Nauvoo Expositor</em> led to his execution by a mob while in jail, after which he was succeeded as his group\u2019s president by Brigham Young. For the point, name this founder of Mormonism.", "answer": "Joseph<b> Smith</b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A temple called the Serapeum served as one of these institutions but was destroyed by a Christian mob in 391 CE. Ptolemy I was inspired by Ashurbanipal\u2019s creation of one of these to build one with hundreds of thousands of papyrus scrolls. For the point, name these cornerstones of learning, whose\u201cGreat\u201d one at Alexandria was an ancient Wonder of the World.", "answer": "<b> library</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Thorismund became king after his father died in battle against these people in Gaul. One ruler of these people took the gift of Honoria\u2019s ring as a marriage proposal, beginning a campaign that ended at the Catalaunian Plains against Theodoric and Flavius Aetius [AYE-tee-us]. Another leader of these people, Bleda, was killed by his brother while on a hunting trip. For the point, name these nomadic people who lost the Battle of Chalons [sha-LONE] under their leader, Attila.", "answer": "<b> Hun</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "After this event, Boston Corbett killed the perpetrator, Lewis Powell and Mary Surratt were executed, and Samuel Mudd was imprisoned for providing aid to the perpetrator. It occurred shortly before the scream \u201cSic semper tyrannis!\u201d and a jump from the Presidential box during a showing of \u201cOur American Cousin\u201d at Ford Theater. For the point, name this 1865 event in which John Wilkes Booth shot and killed the U.S. President.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> of Abraham<b> Lincoln</b> (accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This company attempted to recruit people working for its competitors in Operation SLOG. Barack Obama\u2019s former campaign manager David Plouffe advises this company, which was founded by Travis Kalanick. In 2013, it partnered with Home Depot to deliver Christmas trees in select cities, though this competitor of Lyft has been criticized for classifying its drivers as independent contractors and its automatic \u201csurge pricing\u201d. For the point, name this controversial smartphone taxicab-hailing app.", "answer": "<b> Uber</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Ida Klaus created a modified version of this law for New York City. The Supreme Court upheld the legality of an organization that was formed out of this law after a challenge from Jones & Laughlin Steel. This law didn\u2019t apply to federal government and railroad workers. Along with the Norris-Laguardia Act, the Taft-Hartley Act weakened many parts of this law. The National Labor Relations Board was created out of this law in order to ensure collective bargaining. For the point, name this 1935 New Deal labor law.", "answer": "<b> Wagner</b> Act (or the<b> National Labor Relations Act</b> of 1935)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The density of this entity can be approximated by George Gamow\u2019s liquid drop model, as done in the semi-empirical mass formula. The strong force is only experienced in this location. While testing J.J. Thomson\u2019s plum-pudding model, Rutherford discovered the mass of an atom was concentrated in this location. For the point, name this central part of an atom composed of protons and neutrons.", "answer": "<b> nucleus</b> of an atom (prompt on atom alone until mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "This composer wrote a Requiem for the author of<em> The Betrothed</em>, Alessandro Manzoni. In one opera by this compeer, the high priest Zaccaria opposes Nebuchadnezzar and a chorus of Hebrew slaves sings\u201cVa, pensiero.\u201d This composer of<em> Nabucco</em> wrote an opera in which the guard Radames [rah-dah-meez] falls in love with the title Egyptian princess and which features the \u201cTriumphal March\u201d. For the point, name this Italian composer of<em> Aida</em> [ah-EE-dah].", "answer": "Giuseppe<b> Verdi</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "Fellow artist Eug`ene Delacroix [oo-ZHEN dell-ah-QUA] served as a live model for this painting. A hatchet in the foreground of this painting suggests that its subjects may have resorted to cannibalism. A man with a red cloak over his head mourns the loss of his son in this painting, in which a shirtless man on a barrel can be seen waving a red and white cloth. For the point, name this work by Th\u00b4eodore G\u00b4ericault [tay-oh-DOOR ZHAIR-ee-COH] depicting the aftermath of French maritime disaster.", "answer": "The<b> Raft of the Medusa</b> or La<b> Radeau de la Meduse</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "One participant in this event tried to commit suicide by ingesting expired cyanide and jumping into a river, but the river was only a few inches deep. That man and several others had been organized by a man codenamed Apis to carry out this action. This event led to the July Ultimatum and was perpetrated by a member of the Black Hand named Gavrilo Princip. For the point, name this event, the killing of an Austrian Archduke that is considered to have sparked World War One.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> of Archduke<b> Franz Ferdinand</b> (accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s failure to throw out Sid Bream preceded 20 years of losing seasons for the Pittsburgh Pirates. After Jose Canseco, he was the second player to hit 40 home runs and steal 40 bases. He was accused of using performance-enhancing drugs by reporters for the San Francisco Chronicle, and of perjury in an investigation of Victor Conte\u2019s BALCO. For the point, name this former Giant outfielder who, in 2001, hit a season-record 73 home runs, part of his career-record 763 homers.", "answer": "Barry Lamar<b> Bonds</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "One poem about this conflict talks about how the dead \u201clived, felt dawn, saw sunset glow.\u201d Another poem about this conflict asks \u201cWhat passing bells for those who die as cattle\u201d; that poem\u2019s author was heavily influenced by his friend Siegfried Sassoon. One poem about this war considers the title, which is taken from Horace, \u201cThe old Lie\u201d. For the point, name this war, the setting of \u201cDolce et Decorum est\u201dby Wilfred Owen and \u201cIn Flanders\u2019 Fields,\u201d which was fought between 1914 and 1918.", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> or<b> First World War</b> (or<b> WWI</b> or<b> Great War</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}